Kiprono Elijah Koech | Résumé

Nairobi, Kenya

in: https://www.linkedin.com/in/kipronokoech

Summary

Highly analytical, ingenious, and results-oriented data scientist and statistician focusing on being a grounded researcher providing solutions to real-world problems through data analysis and modelling. Possessing working knowledge of Python programming and database management using SQL with the application in predictive modelling and data analysis, among other areas.

Key Skills

Areas of Expertise

Applied Statistics

Machine Learning

Deep Learning Com

Computer Vision Data Mining

Data Visualization

Reproducible Research

Business Intelligence and Analytics

Applied Mathematics

Database Management

Tools and Technologies.

SQL Git Version Control

R (familiar)

LATEX LE

TensorFlow and Keras AWS

HTML and CSS

Tableau | Looker | Microsoft Office Suite

Docker

SPSS

Soft skills...

Python

Dependable

Very quick and eager to learn

Thriving in solving complex tasks

Linux

Excellent Communicator

Education

Stellenbosch University

Certificate: Master's Degree in Applied Mathematics (Data Science)

Research area: Deep Learning/ Computer vision

Cape Town, South Africa

Feb 2020 - Apr 2022

Stellenbosch University

Certificate: Master's Degree in Mathematical Sciences, Cum Laude

Research area: Machine Learning and Computer Vision

Cape Town, South Africa

Jan 2019 - Nov 2019

Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology

Certificate: Bachelor's Degree in Science (Statistics), First Class Honors

Nairobi, Kenya Sep 2013 – Nov 2017

Work Experience

Data Intelligence Analyst, Sun King Limited

Nairobi, Kenya

A brief: Analyzing data to drive sales and improve the collection of follow-on revenues.

January 2023 - To Date

• Design pilots, analyze data, and make recommendations to help improve sales of our products and promote the collection of follow-on revenues on products under a loan.

Data Science Intern, Kenya Meteorological Department

Nairobi, Kenya

A brief: Working on techniques to improve weather forecasting.

April 2022 – October 2022
arning recurrent neural network

- Working on improving weather forecasting through the application of machine learning recurrent neural network models,
- Testing new parametrization schemes and,
- Optimizing data assimilation procedures for Weather Research and Forecasting (WRF) model initialization.

Research Fellow, Science of Intelligence

Berlin, Germany

A brief: Worked on a computer vision project at Technische Universität Berlin.

Feb 2021 – Aug 2021

• Worked on action recognition problem for wildlife

Data Science Technical Mentor, Great Learning - Olympus

A brief: A mentorship and tutoring role for data science students.

(Remote) Texas, U.S.A *Nov* 2020 - Aug 2021

 Mentored and tutored 6 students per semester taking a Data Science and Business Analytics course at Olympus, attaining 100% successful completion of the course.

Data Assistant, PACT-Timiza

Kisii and Migori, Kenya

A brief: Data entry, management, and analysis role involving HIV patients information.

Jan 2018 – Dec 2018

- Managed HIV patients data for over 10,000 clients. This involved entering information on the paper into the I.Q care database; analyze the data to locate clients with poor adherence and recommend follow-up; and data quality checks.
- Follow-up reduced the cases of poor adherence to anti-retroviral by over 70% and be able to close cases as required. Rectified an event that almost led to the loss of 2300 data points due to system failure. The by-product of this was setting up a more robust backup pipeline.
- Worked as a Data Clerk for the first 2 months, then promoted to Data Assistant.

Statistician Intern, South Nyanza (SONY) Sugar Company

Migori, Kenya

A brief: An internship working with factory data in a sugar company.

Jun 2017 - Dec 2017

- Analyzed factory data to explain production trends and seasonality phenomena.
- Particularly analyzed downtime data and reported variables that are most significant in impacting the extent of downtime. Upon implementation, there was a 42% drop in downtime in 2018 compared to 2017.

Projects

- 1. Fruit Detection | Skills: Python, TensorFlow and Keras, Computer Vision
 - o In this project, Mask R-CNN and YOLOv5 are deployed in context from fruit detection on outdoor images (apples and mangoes).
 - The two models achieved on-par state-of-the-art results attaining 93% and 88% in F1 scores for mango and apple images, respectively... more information in GitHub.
- 2. Reviews Classification | Skills: Web scraping, Sklearn, machine learning algorithms
 - \circ This project involves scraping over 200k reviews using Scrapy and classifying them as positive or negative using different Sklearn models. Also, dealing with the issue of data imbalance.
 - SVM classifier was the best in this application achieving an F1 score of 89%... the code is in this GitHub repo.
- 3. Crop Disease Classification | Skills: Python, TensorFlow and Keras, Computer Vision
 - o This is a classification problem applied to Agriculture. This project was presented as a solution to a Zindi Challenge and ranked as top 15% solution...more information in GitHub.

Award and Honors

Golden Key Award for being among the top 15% academic performers among the 2019 cohort. (2020-2022)

African Institute for Mathematical Sciences (AIMS) Scholarship for MSc Mathematics at S.U. (2019-2010) & (2020-2021)

Award for Excellence, African Institute for Mathematical Sciences(AIMS)

(Jan 2019 - Nov 2019)

Vice-Chancellor's Academic Award, the best student in Bachelor of Science (Statistics option)

(2014/2015, 2015/2016, and 2016/2017 academic years)

First place, Mathematics contest with 1954 contestants (2012)

Groups and Societies

- Computer Vision and Remote Sensing Group at Technische Universität Berlin, Germany [1]
- Data Science Research Group at African Institute for Mathematical Sciences, South Africa [1]
- Golden Key International Honour Society
- Kenya National Society of Statisticians

The Hobbies and Interests

- Volunteering and Charity work.
- Playing puzzle games like Rubik's Cube and Sudoku game.
- Reading books. Currently reading "The Compounding Effect" by Darren Hardy.

Last updated: Sunday 4th June, 2023 at 23:56